{"tossups": [{"question": "During one of these campaigns, a king died with his son John Tristan, who had been born in Damietta during a different one of these campaigns. The leader of one of these campaigns, Simon de Montfort, was killed while besieging Toulouse. The Albigensian one of these conflicts defeated the Cathars in the south of France, and Louis IX was canonized for his efforts in the seventh and eighth ones of these against Egypt and Tunisia. For ten points, name these conflicts, called by the Pope, that targeted religious enemies.", "answer": "<b> crusades</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A player who won a Super Bowl for this team started his career under a 43-year, $40 million contract with the USFL. That man replaced a quarterback on this team who threw \u201cThe Catch\u201d to Dwight Clark in the 1982 NFC Championship Game. During the 2016 preseason, this team\u2019s backup quarterback refused to stand for the national anthem, beginning a national protest movement. For ten points, name this NFL team whose quarterbacks have included Steve Young, Joe Montana, and Colin Kaepernick.", "answer": "<b> San Francisco 49ers</b> (accept either or both)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man called the Turnip Day session and attacked the \u201cdo-nothing\u201d Eightieth Congress for failing to pass legislation. The Conservative Coalition opposed this architect of a \u201cFair Deal,\u201d whose veto of the Taft-Hartley Act was overridden by Congress. This President negotiated at the Potsdam Conference after he replaced his late predecessor. \u201cThe buck stopped\u201d at the desk of, for ten points, what U.S. President who oversaw the end of World War II?", "answer": "Harry S.<b> Truman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The over-creation of these parts of speech through the use of derivational morphology creates their\u201czombie\u201d type. Socrates defined these parts of speech as \u201conoma\u201d in the<em> Cratylus</em>. Classifiers on these types of speech are found in Chinese and Turkish to add quantifiers. Articles are sometimes placed before these parts of speech in English in order to start a type of \u201cphrase\u201d contrasted with verb phrases. For ten points, name this part of speech, often defined as including persons, places, things, or ideas.", "answer": "<b> noun</b>s", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {}, {"question": "This man killed the Sheriff of Lanark, William Heselrig, at Lanark. Blind Harry chronicled the life of this man, an ally of Andrew Moray. John de Menteith captured this man, who was hung, drawn, and quartered in 1305. This subject of John Balliol was defeated at Falkirk, inspiring Robert the Bruce to take up his cause. For ten points, name this opponent of Edward Longshanks and winner at the Battle of Stirling Bridge, a hero of Scottish independence.", "answer": "William<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This rebellion was inspired by the pamphlet \u201cGood Words for Exhorting the Age\u201d and originated among the Hakka people. The Ever Victorious Army was essential in putting down this rebellion under the leadership of General Gordon, who gained a nickname from that campaign. This rebellion\u2019s leader, a man who claimed to be the younger brother of Jesus, was found dead in his palace in Nanjing. For ten points, name this 19th century rebellion, led by Hong Xiuquan, that tried to establish a Heavenly Kingdom in China.", "answer": "<b> Taiping</b> Rebellion (accept synonyms, like uprising or civil war)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Vladimir Putin said he did not mean to scare this leader after he brought his pet labrador to a meeting in 2007. The term \u201cGroKo\u201d was coined to describe this leader\u2019s most recent coalition with the SPD. This leader\u2019s country received a record breaking 1.1 million asylum seekers in 2015. Wolfgang Schauble serves as Finance Minister under this leader, who often makes the \u201ctriangle of power\u201d hand gesture. For ten points, name this current Chancellor of Germany, often cited as the world\u2019s most powerful woman?", "answer": "Angela<b> Merkel</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This founder of the Keystone Bridge company began his career as a telegraph operator. He hired the Pinkertons to put down the Homestead Strike and pioneered the idea of vertical integration, in which he owned the entire supply chain.<em> The Gospel of Wealth</em> was written by, for ten points, what corporate titan whose company became U.S. Steel in 1901 and whose wealth sponsored a music hall in New York City?", "answer": "Andrew<b> Carnegie</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "As Governor, this man ended Gabriel Prosser\u2019s slave rebellion. This man\u2019s support of the American Colonization Society was rewarded when a newly founded African country named its capital after him. This man received all but one electoral vote in one election and promoted a foreign policy that opposed European colonial efforts in the Western Hemisphere. For ten points, name this fifth president of the United States, the successor of James Madison and namesake of an important doctrine.", "answer": "James<b> Monroe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This government was advised by the<em> Roju</em> and used red seal ships for trade. Only the<em> nanban</em> were allowed by this government to enter its country, as per Sakoku law, which banned foreign influence. This period began when a leader defeated forces loyal to Toyotomi Hideyoshi at the Battle of Sekigahara, and ended when Matthew Perry\u2019s black ships arrived. Ieyasu founded, for ten points, which Japanese shogunate that was ended by the 1868 Meiji restoration?", "answer": "<b> Tokugawa</b> shogunate (accept<b> Edo</b> period)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This movement began in Arnold due to hosiery falling out of fashion. The Pentrich riots were started by Jeremiah Brandreth, a former member of this movement. Members of this</b> <b>movement executed William Horsfall and attacked Rawfolds (+)</b> <b>Mill. The Swing Riots</b> <b>was an agricultural version of this movement, which was suppressed by the 1812 Frame Breaking Act. A man named Ned who legendarily smashed two (*) </b> knitting frames inspired, for ten points, what anti-Industrial Revolution movement in England that opposed new technologies?", "answer": "<b> Luddite</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Near the end of this program, Deke Slayton controlled personnel assignments, and was himself chosen to be its last crew member. As a show of</b><em><b> d\u00b4etente</b></em><b>, this program collaborated with the (+)</b><em><b> Soyuz</b></em><b> program in a 1975 docking mission. James Lovell commanded one phase of this program, which suffered an explosion and aborted its (*) </b> landing mission. Seventeen numbered missions were part of, for ten points, what American space program that \u201cwon\u201d the space race by landing Neil Armstrong on the Moon?", "answer": "<b> Apollo</b> Program (accept<b> Apollo 13</b> after \u201cJames Lovell\u201d is read; accept<b> Apollo 11</b> after\u201cNeil Armstrong\u201d is read; do not accept or prompt on other answers, such as the American space program)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>John Steuart Curry depicted this man in front of a wagon train, a fire, and a tornado, holding a Bible and a gun in outstretched arms. This man received funding and support</b> <b>from Gerrit Smith, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, and the rest of the (+)</b> <b>\u201cSecret Six.\u201d</b> <b>After the sacking of Lawrence, this man led a group of settlers that murdered five people at Pottawatomie Creek, one of the \u201cBleeding Kansas\u201d conflicts. (*) </b> Robert E. Lee led a Marine detachment that captured this man in October 1859 from a Virginia armory. For ten points, name this American abolitionist who was executed after his failed raid on Harpers Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This city is home to the Erechtheion, a temple probably designed by Mnesicles [neh-sih-klees] and financially supported by the treasury of the (+) Delian League, which was based in this city. This city was connected to its port, several kilometers away at Piraeus, by the Long Walls, which were ordered destroyed in (*) </b> 404 BC after this city lost the Peloponnesian War. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state where Pericles ordered the building of the Parthenon on the Acropolis.", "answer": "<b> Athens</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>Holders of this position possessed the Heirloom Seal of the Realm and ranked</b> <b>their consorts and concubines. The first holder of this position, a (+) Legalist, ended</b> <b>the Warring States period, burned books, and was buried with an army of terracotta</b> <b>warriors. The (*)</b> Mandate of Heaven empowered, for ten points, what position held by Qin Shi Huangdi and hundreds of other Middle Kingdom leaders? ANSWER:<b> Emperor of China</b> (or<b> Huangdi</b> before mentioned; prompt on \u201cSon of Heaven;\u201d prompt on partial answers, like \u201crulers of China\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}